

contact

jesfordphd@gmail.com linkedin.com/in/jesford 206.446.6874

profile

Data Scientist specializing in Python, machine learning, experimental design, practical statistics and problem solving. I enjoy writing clean robust code with thorough documentation, exploring new methods and technologies, and teaching others the tools to work more efficiently.

website

jesford.github.io

experience

2016-now

N Backcountry.com

Data Scientist

- Advanced in-house algorithm for cross-channel attribution, incorporating off-line customer behavior to inform optimal marketing bid adjustments.
- Measured incremental sales impact of novel customer service initiatives against holdout customer pool created using nearest neighbors.
- Led design, execution, & measurement of tests to optimize salesperson interactions via customer segmentation, product taxonomy, method and timing of contact, using resampling methods and hypothesis testing.
- Automated processes and nightly builds of database summary tables to enforce reproducibility and reduce reporting time for analysts by 99%.
- Built Python package (cx_Oracle wrapper) for easily interfacing with Oracle DB from Python, removing multi-tool headache for analytics teams.
- Pulled and aggregated messy data from diverse sources (Oracle DB, Adobe Analytics, third-party APIs, Google Trends, Social Media), and worked across departments to enforce data quality standards.
- Measured sales impact of activities performed by customer service department using multivariate linear regression.
- Facilitated knowledge transfer, and reduced detrimental effects of employee turnover, by organizing GitLab Groups and teaching best practices for documentation and version control.
- Founded and led bi-weekly tutorial and workshop series to elevate technical skills among Backcountry analysts and engineers.

GitHub

@jesford

tech skills

♥ Python (expert) Jupyter, Pandas, NumPy, Scikit-Learn, SciPy, Matplotlib, Seaborn

Git
GitHub
SQL
R
Travis-CI
Bash/csh
cron
C/C++
IDL
Sphinx
HTML/CSS
Django
AWS

M=X

OS X

Linux

2015–2016 **eScience Institute, University of Washington**

Data Science Postdoctoral Fellow

- Author of Python package for statistical modeling of galaxy clusters.
 - github.com/jesford/cluster-lensing
- Machine Learning algorithms for hazardous asteroid detection.
- Mentor for the Data Science for the Social Good summer program.
- Invite-only Hackathon by DataKind, addressing Seattle traffic safety.

education

Ph.D. in Physics, 2015 University of British Columbia

B.Sc. in Physics, 2008 *Minor in Mathematics* University of Nevada, Reno

2009–2015 University of British Columbia

Vancouver, BC

Seattle, WA

Park City, UT

Research Assistant (Graduate Student)

- Complex model building, fit optimization, bootstrapping, systematic bias testing, uncertainty estimation and propagation, parallel processing.
- Champion for open data, publicly released 2 new astronomical catalogs.

2007 **NASA Jet Propulsion Laboratory**

Pasadena, CA

Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship: ran simulations for scientific mission cost-benefit analysis & publicly released the datasets.

mentorship & teaching

2016	Data Science Mentor Predicting food-borne illnesses from online rev	Data Science for the Social Good, UW riews & social media
2015–2016	Software Carpentry Instructor Teaching technical computing skills to scientist and Bash; certified Software Carpentry Instruction	
2013–2014	Future Science Leaders Fellow Mentoring exceptional high school students in	Science World, Vancouver physics & astronomy projects
2010–2015	Presentations & Outreach Developed, lead, & open-sourced dozens of c	UBC lassroom science activities
2009–2014	Academic Teaching Taught undergraduate physics courses; mento	UBC ored other graduate instructors

awards

2015	Data Science Postdoctoral Fellowship Moore/Sloan Data Science & WRF Innova	eScience Institute, UW ation in Data Science Fellowship
2011	Four-Year-Fellowship Awarded to the top doctoral students	Department of Physics & Astronomy, UBC
2009	Graduate Entrance Scholarship Awarded to the top incoming graduate st	Department of Physics & Astronomy, UBC tudents
2008	Regents' Scholar Award \$5000 prize awarded annually to a single academic achievements, leadership abilit	9
2008	Westfall Scholar Award Award for the highest GPA in Physics	Department of Physics, University of Nevada

leadership

2017	Co-organizer: Salt Lake PyLadies Organizer and contributor to the local chapter of PyLadies, an international mentorship group for women who code in Python	
2015	Site Host: Software+Data Carpentry Instructor & Helper Retreat Organized and hosted the Seattle site for this worldwide event on improving teaching techniques and workshop materials	
2013	Lead Organizer: Graduate Student Career Workshop Vancouver, BC Coordinated full-day workshop for Canadian Astronomical Society conference	
2012-2014	Coordinator: Cosmology Group Weekly Seminar)

publications & presentations

- 9 peer-reviewed journal publications, including 5 first-author publications
- More than 25 conference & academic presentations, including 6 invited talks

interests

Snowboarding (former sponsored athlete), hiking, softball, disc golf, camping, music